So welcome back, everyone.
So on Monday, Tatsu did an excellent job
of describing a high level overview of GPUs
and how to think about performance and all the quirks
that come with GPUs.
This lecture is going to be a continuation of that, where
we're going to dive more deeply into the code,
write some Triton kernels, and as well as do some benchmarking
and profiling.
So just to start, just to refresh
what's going on with GPUs, here is
a simplified diagram of what a typical GPU looks like.
There's memory, and then the actual GPU chip.
And just to keep in your head what are
the characteristics of a GPU.
So of course, we're talking about NVIDIA GPUs,
but Tatsu also talked about CPUs, and there's AMD and so on.
But focusing on NVIDIA GPUs.
We've had multiple generations, from A100s, to H100s, to B200s.
And in each generation, you have a GPU.
It has a number of Streaming Multiprocessors, or SMs.
And the number of SMs is about 100, between 100 and 200.
So that hasn't really changed that much.
And then within the individual SM, there's a set of registers.
So B200s have 65,000 registers for a total of 256K per SM.
And this also hasn't changed that much.
In addition, there's a L1 cache as well as shared memory.
So remember, these are the same memory,
shared memory you can control.
L1, you can't.
This is per SM.
And this is in the same order ballpark of size.
And then there's L2 cache.
And this is not per SM, this is for the whole chip.
And this is a bit larger.
And then finally, you have a High Bandwidth Memory, or HBM,
which is large.
And you see that this is the number that's
actually going up quite a bit.
OK.
And then in addition to size, you
can think about what's happening with the bandwidth.
And essentially, it's inversely correlated.
So registers are very fast, L1 is slightly less fast,
L2 is less fast, and High Bandwidth Memory is the slowest.
Although eight terabytes a second
is still not that slow in the grand scheme of things.
So this is the main hierarchy you should have in your head.
Large memory is slow and far but big.
And fast memory like registers and L1 resides on the SM.
It's local and it's fast, but small.
OK, that's the environment we're dealing with.
OK, so then, how do you program a GPU?
So the program model is as follows.
So there's notions of threads, which
each thread executes a piece of code
on a small part of the data.
So each one of these arrows, you can think about it as a thread.
These threads are organized into thread blocks,
also known as Concurrent Thread Arrays, or CTAs.
And this is a group of threads.
And then finally, you have a collection of thread blocks
which forms the grid.
So when you launch a kernel, you're basically
launching a grid of threads and thread blocks to all parallel
simultaneously do some computation.
OK, so this is simplified.
There's some other things that are happening.
For example, there's H100s and B200s also
have thread block clusters, which
are clusters of thread blocks that
enable some amount of distribution memory.
Also, B200s have tensor memory.
Now for tensor cores, which is somewhere between registers
and shared memory.
Some of these things are invisible to the programmer,
but they are in the hardware.
But we won't worry about them for this intro lecture.
OK, so one thing you might ask about
is, why do we have thread blocks?
Why can't we just have a grid of threads,
and each thread just takes a piece of data
and does something?
And this would be normally fine if all you want to do
is element-wise operations, which we'll see.
For example, GeLU is an activation function
that applies element-wise.
And threads are pretty natural.
Each thread processes one element.
So it's like for i equals ranging over your data set.
But for operations that involve communicating with threads,
such as softmax or matrix multiplication,
this view isn't really enough.
And the reason is that, well, it could be enough
if you were willing to pay the cost of writing and reading HBM.
Because then you can still have-- for example, in a matrix
we'll see later, you can just have every element in a cell.
It goes and computes that element of the matrix.
And it can just read and write HBM.
But as we've noticed, HBM is very slow,
so this would not be a good strategy.
So instead, what we should do is use shared memory,
which is local to SM.
And what the thread block allows you to think about
is a collection of threads that are all going
to access this shared memory.
So consequently, you can think about a thread block,
one of these thread blocks is being scheduled
on one of these semantic--
not semantic, streaming multiprocessors.
And it does its thing.
And what it's going to do is it's
going to read a bunch of data from HBM
and then process it where the processing might involve
communication between the threads via the shared memory,
and then writes it back out.
OK.
So this is a critical piece that comes up.
Later, we'll talk about tiling, and that's the whole game here.
OK, in Triton, in fact, which we'll see as a primary way
that we're going to write kernels these days,
we're going to think natively in thread blocks.
And I think once you get the hang of thinking
of thread blocks, this makes a lot of sense
and makes your life a lot easier, as we'll see.
OK, so the programming model is fairly simple, I think.
There's threads, thread blocks, and grids.
I think things get a bit more complicated,
is the interaction between the programming
model and the hardware.
So the programming model is actually very nice.
It provides abstraction of the hardware.
When you can write a kernel, all you have to know
is that there's a bunch of thread blocks.
You define them and then define what
computations each thread within the block or the thread block
has to do.
And those are just writing-- it's like writing Python.
So that part isn't hard.
And in fact, if you don't care about--
if you just care about correctness,
that's all you need to know.
But in practice, the performance is
very sensitive to the hardware.
And so you need to really deeply understand the hardware
to obtain high performance.
And in fact, the whole reason we're
talking about GPUs and kernels is
that you're trying to squeeze out performance.
So there's these two levels here where
you're trying to understand the computation,
and that is only a part of the programming model.
But how fast it runs is going to be strongly
dependent on the hardware.
OK, so I'm going to give you some examples of why this
matters, and some of this will be review
from what Tatsu talked about.
But hopefully it will reinforce some of these concepts.
So I think there will be around five different examples.
And this is just to give you a flavor of the considerations.
So there's something called warps, which I didn't talk about.
So in the very simplified view, warps
are not really part of this clean picture of the programming
model.
You have threads and thread blocks or grids.
Technically, you can also access the warps,
but you don't have to when you're just programming.
So what is a warp?
So each thread block, remember, is a collection of threads.
But these threads are actually grouped into warps.
And there's basically 32 threads per warp.
So for example, if you have 64 threads in a thread block,
there's two warps, the first 32 and the second 32.
And as Tatsu mentioned last time,
all threads within a warp, all of these T's, must
execute the same instruction in lockstep on SM.
So every cycle, they have to execute
exactly the same instruction.
And control divergence is when different threads within a warp
need to actually execute different instructions.
For example, if you have branching, if something,
then A else B.
And then what happens is that you can only
do the A's in your threads in your warp,
and then you do the B. So this gets sequential.
So this is bad and inefficient, and that's
why branching is something you want to generally avoid.
One thing that's, I think, really cool about warps
is that an SM actually is running multiple warps.
There's a warp scheduler, and there's
a bunch of resident warps that are about to run.
Each warp has some--threads have registers.
And the SM can switch between them with zero cost.
Right, this is not true in general, like on a CPU.
But this way that it's designed is to hide latency.
So this is important, because one
of the warps is, for example, reading from HBM,
which remember is very expensive,
can take 100 cycles or something.
You don't want to just sit around waiting for that warp
to do nothing.
You switch immediately to another warp
where it can actually do some tensor core operations.
OK, so that's one thing to note about the warp.
And another reason why warp comes up
is this idea of occupancy.
More specifically, warp occupancy.
So each thread, just the hardware constraint
says that each thread can use at most 255 registers.
OK, and so what happens is that the SM has
a fixed number of registers.
So the more registers each thread is using,
the fewer threads you can have.
That's just math.
And that can reduce your occupancy.
But that's not necessarily bad, because if you
have fewer threads.
But each thread is doing more work, that can actually be good.
So occupancy is something that you can measure,
but it's not necessarily the larger, the better.
Because there are some other tradeoffs here.
And in fact, an example where you
might want to have fewer threads is this idea
of thread coarsening, where let's say
you have an element-wise operation
and you can have one thread just perform work on one element.
OK, so then you have a lot of threads.
But you can also say each thread processes multiple elements.
Like a constant, maybe eight.
So that gives you fewer threads, which
makes scheduling and these things easier,
but each thread is doing more work.
So if your threads are very light,
maybe you want to fatten them up a little bit.
OK.
So just as an example of what might happen here.
So suppose you have a block, a thread block
with 128 threads in it.
And each thread is using 160 registers.
OK.
So there's a hardware constraint.
So the B200s have a maximum of registers of 65,000 per SM.
And it also has a constraint that
says you can't run more than 64 warps at a time.
So then you can go and do some simple math
to compute what is the occupancy here.
So number of registers per thread.
This has to be less than 255.
That's fine.
The number of registers that you're using per block
is the number of threads per block
times the number of registers per thread.
That's about 20,000.
That means you can run at most three blocks on your SM
concurrently.
And then that corresponds to 12 warps.
And because the number of maximum warps is 64,
that means you have an occupancy of 18%.
So we're only running 18% of the total number of warps you have.
And this is because you have a lot of register use per thread.
OK, so this is an example of where I guess this is memory
constraining you in terms of how much compute you can do.
OK, here's another example.
Something called bank conflicts.
This applies to shared memory.
So remember, shared memory is like L1.
It's on an SM.
And just the way the hardware works
is that shared memory is divided into 32 banks, each one four
bytes wide.
OK, so these are my 32 banks, and this is my memory here.
Each bank has many elements here.
So there's a constraint that says every clock cycle,
each bank can only be accessed by one thread, at most
one thread.
Assuming that's not a location.
So for example, if you can't access
this location and this location at the same time.
Which means that if you have multiple threads that
are trying to access the same bank,
the accesses have to be serialized.
And this is called a bank conflict.
In the worst case example, imagine
this were a matrix that was laid out like this.
And you had some operation where 32 threads, you think, wow,
this 32 is so great.
I can massively parallelize this,
and you try to all access this first column.
They're just going to just wait in line.
And this is a 32-way bank conflict,
which is the worst possible setting you can be in.
Now you could say, well, OK, why did you do that?
Just like access rows, of course.
But this is unavoidable, because, for example,
if you're doing a matmul, you have
to access rows of one matrix and columns of another matrix.
And sometimes you do transposes, so you can't always
just get away with choosing the order in which you go down.
For element-wise operations, it's fine.
You can go in any order.
But if you're doing matmuls, you can't
control for every matrix which row major or column
major you're doing.
There are some solutions here, which I won't get into.
Something called swizzling, which arranges your shared
memory so that when you're going through,
you can avoid bank conflicts.
OK, so that's another consideration.
And when you're profiling, you can look at the bank conflicts,
you can look at occupancy.
And you can see what's happening.
A final note which--actually, two more things.
So memory coalescing, which you talked about.
So I'll just really quickly remind people what this is about.
So when you have 32 threads in a warp and they try to access HBM,
the memory accesses actually get combined
into a transaction of 128 bytes, which are called cache lines.
And it goes and fetches it all at once.
So imagine you have memory laid out like this.
This is 32.
And in the best case, which is called full coalescing,
all the threads are accessing the same cache line.
So you have thread 1 accessing M00, thread 2 accessing M01,
and so on.
Which means that all at once, you're
going to grab this entire cache line.
Right, and whereas if you go down the columns,
then you're going to fetch a lot of memory
here, which you're not going to use.
Same for the second row and so on.
And so this feels similar to bank conflicts,
but it's a very different constraint.
And this is about shared memory, and this is about HBM.
OK.
OK, so final thing, block occupancy.
So thread blocks are, remember, scheduled onto SMs.
But we live in a finite--
logically, you can define as many thread blocks as you want.
But physically on chip, you only have a certain number of SMs.
For example, 148.
So if you launch 160 thread blocks,
then you can only schedule 148 of them.
And then you have to wait until they're done,
and then you schedule the 12.
But what happens if you schedule 12
is that there's a bunch of SMs are just not doing anything.
So that's called low occupancy.
When the last wave of thread blocks
gets fewer than the total maximum number of thread blocks.
OK, so in general, maybe it's a good idea
to make the number of thread blocks divide the SMs.
So maybe just to summarize here, there
is a very elegant programming model
where you have a grid of thread blocks
and the thread blocks have individual threads in them.
And in terms of the memory, HBM is global to everyone.
Shared memory is local to a thread block.
And registers are local to a thread.
But again, all the details of the hardware-- warps,
bank conflicts, memory coalescing, occupancy--
really determine performance.
And many of these details are hard to know, because, I mean,
the profiling tells you a bunch of information.
But you have to know exactly how many SMs there
are and exactly the sizing of everything.
Sometimes the scheduler does something
you don't really have control over what it's doing.
So it's a little messier than the programming model.
OK, I will stop there for questions.
Yeah?
Yes, a quick question.
So Cam, is there a scenario in which you
one can share with them or—like, for example,
in the problem that we see 140 SM [INAUDIBLE] blocks, right.
And we have to launch into two different ways.
Is there no way in which a block can share an SM?
Yeah, so the question is, can a block share an SM?
I think the issue is if you're doing things right, then the—
I guess it depends on the block.
If you have a block that's, for example,
using most of the tensor cores on the SM,
then putting another block there isn't really
going to speed things up.
I think fundamentally, there is this jagged problem
here of unevenness.
Because the blocks have to stay together.
So you can't take this and spread it out over here.
The thing you would do is to change your block size.
So you change the number of blocks
so you don't get this tail here.
Any other questions?
OK, so let's move on.
Hopefully you guys are getting more comfortable with GPUs now.
So now I'm going to talk about benchmarking and profiling.
I'm not going to actually maybe say
that much in terms of content.
But I do want to emphasize the philosophy here, which is,
here's a recipe for success.
You benchmark and profile your code.
You make changes, and you benchmark and profile,
your code again.
And the reason I'm doing benchmarking and profiling
as opposed to teaching you try and earlier
is because you should always just measure
what's going on in your code and figure out
what the bottlenecks are before you start writing kernels.
OK, so benchmarking is basically how long things take.
And it gives you just this end-to-end time.
It doesn't tell you where things are spent.
But nonetheless, it's pretty useful, because ultimately,
that's the thing that you care about, how long things
are running for.
And it also gives you, because it distills things
into one number, you can see how things are scaling, let's say,
with dimension.
So there's a nice tool for benchmarking.
But because this class is language models from scratch,
I'm going to do it from scratch.
But I think I'm doing it just to highlight a few gotchas
with benchmarking.
So let's say we have this operation, matrix multiplication.
So run operation 2 is this wrapper that basically
instantiates two random square matrices of size dimension
by dimension.
And then it returns a function to perform the operation.
OK, so matmul, if you call this, basically
does the matmul of those two random matrices.
OK, the random matrices are generated,
it's just like multiplying the two.
OK, so how do you benchmark?
So the naive thing to do is just start time, run it,
and then stop time.
But there's a few things.
One is that always remember to do your warm-up.
I think I mentioned this on the second lecture,
but I think it's worth emphasizing.
And this is because if you have some things are lazily compiled
and you want to just make sure that that thing is--
that time doesn't factor into.
Because most of the time, you care
about how fast something is, because you're
going to run it over and over again,
so the initial conditions don't really matter.
And then you often want to time it multiple times
because there is some variance.
The proper way to time things is to use these CUDA events that--
a start event and an end event, which you can call record on.
Actually do the computation and then hit the end event record.
And then remember to synchronize to wait for the CUDA threads
to finish, because everything on the GPU
is happening if you have an async.
And this is a synchronization barrier.
And then you record the time.
OK, and then you can do this again, and then again.
And then here, we're just taking the average.
If you are being very particular,
you probably want to maybe look at the whole distribution,
the P95 or whatever.
But we'll just do the average here.
And then one thing that you can do with benchmarking is you can,
let's say, scale up your matrices
and see how the time changes.
And you can see that in this case, matrix multiplication, as
expected, it should grow cubically.
But notice that there is this flaw where up until you get up
to almost 2,000 dimensional matrices,
things are basically a constant.
Right, and this is because, as we've discussed,
the shapes of these GPUs are built for fairly large matrix
multiplications.
And if you have a 2 by 2 matrix, it's
going to be very inefficient.
OK.
So really quickly on profiling.
Profiling tells you where time is actually spent.
Hopefully all of you are familiar with profiling
and are doing it.
Maybe less obviously, profiling, even
if you don't care about the time,
helps you figure out what's actually
happening under the hood.
Because especially with these high-level languages,
you write some code, and then it runs and you get some result.
And sometimes it can be just good to understand
what's actually going on.
So PyTorch has a built-in profiler.
In your assignment, you'll use Nsight,
which gives you more details.
But we're going to skip that in the interest of time.
So let's start with just if you add two numbers and-- or sorry,
two tensors in PyTorch, again, a run
operation creates two random matrices
and applies the operation.
So in profiling, I'm warming up.
And then I'm just putting this profiling
context and doing the run.
And then let's look at what the profile looks like for just a
plus b in PyTorch.
Normally doing PyTorch, you probably don't think about it.
It's like, OK, well, these two tensors just get added.
So what's actually going on underneath the hood?
Right, so if you look at the things that it's calling,
there is this long name, kernel at CUDA functor add.
So this is basically a kernel that adds two tensors.
And the times aren't going to be that interesting,
because I'm only adding.
So that's going to take 100% of the time.
But this tells you that, well, underneath the hood
there is this thing called add.
What about matmul?
In PyTorch, I'm doing a at b.
Similarly, there is this long name
that describes this particular matmul kernel.
Cutlass f32, f32, 64x64x16, and so on.
Notice that if you change the dimensions--
so now I'm doing a 128 by 128 matmul--
you get actually a different one.
If you look closely, this is 64x64x16, this is 32x32x16.
OK, so underneath the hood, PyTorch,
it looks like you're doing just a at b.
But underneath the hood, there could be all sorts
of things that are happening.
So observations.
Here, you can see which CUDA kernels are actually
being called.
These are generally the ones that have the long names.
And different CUDA kernels are invoked depending
on the tensor dimensions.
The name actually tells you something
about the implementation as well.
So this name.
So cutlass is the NVIDIA CUDA library for linear algebra.
SM100 corresponds to the Blackwell architecture.
So this is a kernel that's specifically
designed for Blackwell.
This is f32.
And then 64x64x16 is the shape of the tile,
which we're going to talk about later when we talk about tiling
in the context of matmuls.
OK, so that's benchmarking profiling.
Just remember to do it.
I think we make you do it on the assignment,
so you have no choice.
OK.
So let's apply this to another example here on the GeLU.
So remember, the GeLU activation function
is this function, which is a typical non-linearity that's
used.
Often, it's approximated with this tanh approximation, which
is more computer friendly.
OK, so naively, if you implement the GeLU,
you can do it in PyTorch just like this.
So you take a tensor, you just take this equation
and you just put it into PyTorch, OK.
That's fine.
And you get some number.
PyTorch also has a built in.
If you call functional GeLU, you can get that version as well.
And you can check that they're the same.
You can run the two GeLU versions
and make sure that the answer is the same for a random input.
There's also something that people probably have discovered.
If you haven't encountered this, this is an important thing to know.
is that you can take any PyTorch function,
you call torch.compile on it, and it
generates another function.
And it does the same thing.
OK, so we have three horses in this race.
We have the naive implementation.
We have the built-in implementation.
We have the compiled implementation.
So we can benchmark them.
Naive takes three.
I guess this is 3.75.
Built-in is much faster and compiled
is much faster as well, but not maybe quite as fast
as built-in.
OK.
So what's happening here?
Why are these things different?
They all compute the same answer,
but they have wildly different performance characteristics.
And so here we can pull up the profiler
and see what's actually going on underneath the hood.
So if you look at the naive GeLU here and just do
a profile, this--something's wrong with this view,
so I'm going to go to this.
So you see that the profile shows how time is being spent.
There's a bunch of different kernels on this binary functor
unary add.
tanh is a kernel here.
And this corresponds to the fact that in PyTorch, when
we write the PyTorch expression, you
look at the computation graph, and
each primitive in the computation
graph is actually realized in the kernel.
Right.
And the reason this is slow is that when you launch a kernel,
the kernel has to read from HBM.
Pull it all the way over to your SM, do the computation,
and write it back.
And then the kernel picks that up from HBM
and then writes it back, and so on and so forth.
So you're doing a lot of reads and writes back and forth.
Because between kernel invocations,
things have to go back to HBM.
So if you look at what the built-in is doing,
this is actually not that interesting.
There's this GeLU CUDA kernel implementation,
which is a single kernel that just implements the GeLU.
And so why does this exist?
Well, because people use GeLU.
So someone wrote a kernel for it and put it
in the standard library.
I mean, there's nothing magical.
So compilation is really interesting here.
I'm not going to say too much about how it works,
but it's really, I think, a fascinating topic where
you can take a naive implementation, which, remember,
it's in PyTorch, it has a computation graph.
And run a compiler.
Which basically, if you look at what's underneath the hood,
it's just a single kernel.
And this is because it's figured out
to look at the computation graph and essentially write
that kernel in Triton.
So you can see that this is actually a Triton kernel.
OK, so naive implementation.
Multiple kernels requires multiple reads and writes
to and from HBM.
There's no kernel fusion here.
This is slow.
The built-in compiler version, there's one kernel.
Basically all the operations in the GeLU
have been fused together into one kernel.
So you read from HBM once, you write to HBM once per element.
And you see that the compiled kernel is a Triton kernel.
OK, so that maybe is a good segue
to talk about what this Triton thing is all about.
Yeah?
Let's see.
I mean, I guess it says CUDA kernel implementation,
so I imagine someone wrote it in CUDA.
OK, any other questions?
Yeah?
Why is the Triton kernel faster than this one?
So why is the Triton kernel faster?
So a Triton kernel is actually not faster in this case.
Oh, sorry.
The compiled kernel is one Triton kernel,
and this is slower than the built-in.
Yeah.
I think last year when I did this, it was actually closer.
But these things change, and it's very hardware dependent.
And I think none of this is terribly optimized.
This is just giving you the general idea here.
OK, so let's write some Triton kernels.
So remember our programming model.
You have a bunch of threads organized by thread groups,
thread blocks, and there's a grid of thread blocks.
And if you were to write in CUDA, which was originally
developed by NVIDIA, and that's been for years the thing
that you do when you write kernels,
the mental model is, what does each thread do?
So you write a piece of code which essentially
has some ID that identifies which
thread you're talking about, and it just executes the code.
So the nice thing about this is that it's very closely related
to what is actually happening underneath the hood.
And it's fine-grained, gives you fine-grained control.
But there's cons here, which is that, remember,
all these threads are in a thread block.
And some operations require them to communicate.
So what has to happen is that they have to synchronize.
And they read from HBM all at once.
And they have to synchronize and do the computation.
And you have to basically do that bookkeeping.
So if you were doing all element-wise operations,
this CUDA is just fine.
It doesn't really matter.
But as you get more complex operations,
then try and provide some value of the abstraction.
So Triton was developed by OpenAI.
I think by now, it's been pretty standard.
You basically specify what each thread block does.
Generally it's powerful enough, especially for this class
that you're getting started.
If you really go and want to exploit every single new feature
of the latest hardware, it might not
give you the full flexibility.
But let's not worry about that.
And the conceptual framework to think about in Triton
is that you're thinking about, what does a block do?
A block is going to load data into shared memory,
operate on it, and write it back to global memory.
So in some sense, these blocks are an intermediate point
between thinking about what individual elements are doing
as well as thinking about the general operation.
And so in PyTorch, you basically define these huge matrices
and you say multiply them together.
And that's the atomic operation.
And a lot of what you're thinking about
is, how do I get things into big matmuls?
Right, and at some level, Triton is
a hybrid between that and the individual elements,
as we'll see.
OK, so let's start with the GeLU example here.
So let's define an 8,000 dimensional vector and start
writing some Triton.
OK, so Triton is basically going to be you write Python.
How many of you have written Triton before?
Just a show of hands.
OK, OK.
Not that many, which is good, because then you won't be bored.
OK, so this is normal PyTorch.
Right, there's no Triton here.
But I'm just preparing.
And so what I'm going to do is I take this tensor,
and I'm going to allocate an output tensor.
OK, because in Triton, we're not thinking functionally anymore.
We're just thinking about moving.
You have to explicitly read and write.
So there's no returning value.
So I'm going to allocate the output
tensor, which I'm going to-- the kernel's going to write to.
And then so this tensor can be arbitrarily big, right.
And I can't generally fit this all into one SM,
because it's just too big.
So I need to break it up into blocks.
So what I'm going to do is you can think about this x
as being this array.
I'm going to chop it up into blocks.
So the total number of elements is 8,000.
I'm just going to set the blocksize to 1,024 for now.
And then I have eight blocks.
OK.
So then I'm going to use this weird syntax to call the kernel.
So Triton GeLU kernel.
This basically in brackets tells me essentially the shape
of the grid.
So basically, this says the grid has num blocks.
Blocks.
And I'm going to, for every one of these blocks,
invoke this function, Triton GeLU kernel, which
I'll talk about in a bit.
I'm going to pass in an x, y num elements and the blocksize.
OK.
All right, so unfortunately, I'm not
going to be able to trace through this,
so I'll just show you what the code looks like here.
So let me get rid of that.
OK, so this is probably the simplest kernel you can imagine.
So when you are looking at the Triton GeLU kernel,
now this is before we had x and y.
So now these are pointers.
Right, you can think about these as just integers,
they're addresses.
So you have to get comfortable with that.
And then we have the number of elements and the blocksize,
which are basically actually passed in from here.
OK, so the way to think about it is that for every block,
we're going to have this function being called.
And what happens is the first thing I'm going to do
is I'm going to wake up.
This block wakes up and says, who am I?
Well, the program ID is-- basically
the PID is basically identifying the block.
So PID would be 0 for this block, 1, 2, and 3 here.
OK, so now I have to figure out what data
I'm going to operate on.
So that's PID times blocksize.
So this is the offset into the x pointer.
So if PID is 0, then start is 0.
If PID is 1, then start is blocksize.
If PID is 2, then it's 2 times blocksize, and so on.
OK.
So now, I'm going to figure out the span I'm operating on.
So offsets is start plus.
This is the Triton library.
A range 0 blocksize, which conceptually gives you
the integers 0 through blocksize minus 1.
So offsets is going to be essentially
for-- let's say block 1, it's going
to be blocksize, blocksize plus 1 all the way to blocks
2 times blocksize minus 1.
OK, so in this case, num elements divides by blocksize.
But in general, that's not the case.
So you'll often see in Triton code, there's this masking.
Which says, well, sometimes if the-- let's say the tensor only
goes up to here.
Then I'm going to form a mask, which
is going to be true up until that point
and false after that point.
And for blocks that are not the final block,
it's going to be just all ones.
OK, so now I've done the setup.
What I do is I read.
And this is basically pointer arithmetic.
So x pointer, remember, is the integer
that specifies the memory location of where x is.
I'm going to add offsets to that,
which gives me the first block size number of elements there.
According to the mask, if I'm masked out,
then I don't read it.
And then now I think you can just think about this as a vector.
And then you do your normal computation.
And then you get y.
And y is the same size as x.
And then you do tl.store y pointer
plus offsets y and the mask.
OK, so this load loads from HBM, does some stuff,
and then it writes back to HBM.
OK, I'm going to stop there and take any questions
about this first Triton kernel.
Yeah?
Yeah.
So the difference is, what is the difference between CUDA?
And for this element-wise, it looks pretty much the same,
right.
And in fact, CUDA is even, I think, simpler,
because it really is element-wise.
You wake up, and you identify the thread.
And then you just operate on that element.
Now the only thing here is that it's
like the vectorized version, where you have a block
and you operate on that block.
Later, we'll see that operating on blocks
is doing more than-- if you do something more
than element-wise, then CUDA is going
to be a lot more annoying to work with.
So a bunch of questions.
Yeah, back there.
How does this relate to if you wanted to use the tensor units?
So how is this related to if you want to use the tensor units?
So I'll later show you what this code actually
compiles down into.
And maybe I'll get back to that.
But the short answer is that you don't control that.
硬件会决定把东西放在哪里。
是吗？
你能具体讲一下
从 HBM 到 shared memory 再到 register 时到底发生了什么吗？
数据实际流动的逐步过程是什么？
对，所以问题是，当
这条语句执行时，实际发生了什么？
简短来说，这在某种意义上是假的。
对，并不是 GPU 实际上
在 GPU 上调用 Triton 库
并且真的在执行这段代码。
这基本上是为了让我们
指定这个计算。
编译器会接收它，我们后面会看到，
并把它写成一种叫做 ptx 的东西，
然后它才会真正干活。
所以从机制上讲就是这么回事，
我稍后会讲到。
如果你问的是概念上的问题，
思考方式是，这个——
x 指针是 HBM 中的一个内存位置。
这基本上指定了一段内存位置。
而 load 会接收那些内存位置
并返回与它们关联的数据。
这里，我有一个名为 x 的局部变量。
在实践中，这通常会
是一个 register 或 shared memory。
Triton 会决定那里怎么做。
在 thread 层级上。
当它被调用时，其实并不清楚。
我是提前安排好了什么会放在 shared memory
什么会放在 register 层级，
还是现在才发生，那就太晚了？
所以这就是所有 thread
都闲置在那里，等待内存刷入的地方。
我确信它已经准备好执行了，这样我们就不会
干坐在那里无所事事，
只是等待数据从 HBM 进来。
对，对。
所以问题是，这实际上什么时候会被执行，
and doesn't this block?
Let me try to come back to this question
when I show you the PTX, and maybe hopefully it
will provide a bit more context on what's happening.
OK, any other questions?
OK, so all the kernels are going to look something like this.
So I do want to make sure people understand
just the general form, which is that you have generally
your inputs, your outputs.
You wake up, you figure out which
index you're going to look at.
You read.
You do some stuff, and then you write to HBM.
OK.
So let's talk about PTX briefly.
So let's see, does this work?
Does this link work?
OK, so when you write Triton, the compiler
generates PTX code, which is this intermediate assembly
language for GPUs.
I am obviously not going to go through all of this,
but just to give you the flavor of what this looks like.
Let me actually start with the observation.
So a few things.
So this is now what a thread is actually doing.
Not a thread block, because that's been compiled away.
And so if you look at--a few notes here.
So this LD global is basically saying load from HBM
into some registers.
And the registers are denoted as the r are integer registers, fr,
floating point registers.
And then you have statements like mov 0 into r5,
mov 0 into r6, and so on.
And then you have multiplication.
You're going to multiply this register by this constant
and then put it into this.
So this code gets executed.
And at the bottom, you should see global store.
So this is writing back into the HBM.
So this gets executed.
This is actually the code that gets executed on a thread.
And Triton is basically a layer up above that.
One other thing to notice is that you see all these blocks
and what's going on there.
And what's going on there is I alluded
to thread coarsening, which is that this is one thread.
But rather than processing a single element,
it's actually processing eight elements.
So the compiler decided that, well, actually, this thread
is pretty lightweight.
It doesn't do that much, so let's just
try to thicken it up a little bit.
So looking at PTX can give you some appreciation for what's
going on underneath the hood.
Yeah?
So it makes this for each individual--[INAUDIBLE]
So the question is, does it make this for each thread?
So this is compiled once.
And it's the same piece of code that each thread runs.
And the way that the thread distinguishes
itself is that this piece of code gets
passed basically the thread ID.
So here, the CTA.x is the block index,
and tid.x is the thread index.
So this basically, if this piece of code is running,
this tells you which block I'm in.
And tid.x tells you which thread inside that block I'm in.
OK.
Any other questions?
And I'm trying to figure out how to--OK.
OK, so that's generally a flavor of your first Triton kernel
load from HBM, compute, right back to HBM.
And then we saw the PTX, which is the grungy what actually
happens underneath the hood.
There's still a lot of things that are not specified in PTX.
Like, for example, which SM things are operating on
and the warps and everything.
A lot of those are hardware controlled,
so you don't even see.
Yeah?
So PTX code is generated by the compiler, not something
that you would normally code?
It looks like it's assembly code.
Yeah, so the question is, is PTX just generated by the compiler?
So there are people who do write PTX
if you really think you're better than the compiler.
And I think the NVIDIA compilers are generally pretty mature,
but some other accelerators that are less developed.
I think sometimes you just have to reach in
and actually handhold a bit more.
But generally, yeah, you shouldn't need to do that.
Yeah?
My work will get scheduled onto an SM.
I'll get to that tf.load and it's almost
like a CPU trap call where I'm just waiting
for something to happen.
And now I am twiddling my thumbs and some other work
will get scheduled over me.
And then it will do operations.
Now that the upload is done,
then I'll reschedule that work and then I'll continue on.
Is that—Yeah, that's right.
So just to repeat the question or the comment.
So if you look at this triangle code,
these statements, this load, is going
to block for some number of cycles.
And then so this is running on some thread
on some warp on some SM.
And remember, the SM is running multiple warps at the same time.
So when you get to that point, it
can just find another warp to run.
And then when this is done, the warp scheduler
comes back and takes over.
Why do you?
Sorry.
Oh, sorry.
I recall from.
Yeah, so the question is, why four warp schedulers?
I don't exactly know the reason behind that.
OK, so now let's go through some other examples.
Maybe just as a quick preview.
We're going to do three more examples.
GeLU is the simplest form.
Even though the computation has a lot of messiness.
It's just element-wise.
So conceptually, in the context of this lecture,
is actually very simple.
Now we're going to look at softmax, where now you're
going to have to do reduction.
But in this case, we're going to think about the case
where a row fits on a block.
And then we're going to consider the case where
a row doesn't fit on a block, and then we're
going to go up to matmul.
And then hopefully by that point,
you'll have all the ingredients that you
need to do the assignment and implement flash attention.
OK.
So so far, we looked at element-wise operations.
Now let's think about other operations
that aggregate over multiple values.
So remember what softmax does.
Let's just think of it as a matrix.
You exponentiate and normalize each row of a matrix.
OK, so this is used in attention and used in generating output
probabilities.
Generally a good thing to do.
So let's just start with a naive implementation
and just keep track of what's happening.
So here, I'm defining this tensor.
And here's the naive implementation.
Actually, I think this is on assignment one.
OK, anyway.
So here, I have an M by N matrix.
And so I need to, for every row, compute the--
I'm going to compute the max of each row.
And this is for numerical stability.
I'm going to subtract off the max.
And then I'm going to exponentiate element-wise.
And I'm going to sum and compute the normalization.
constant for every row.
And I'm going to divide.
And then that's it.
OK.
So if you count the number of reads and writes, remember,
this is just plain PyTorch.
So this is a different kernel.
This is a different kernel.
And unless you call torch.compile,
these are going to be different operations.
And each operation is going to read and write, read
and write from HBM.
OK, so you have five MN reads, three MN writes.
And in principle, you should really only have much fewer.
OK, so this is a piece of code.
Makes sense.
Everyone should be familiar with what the softmax is doing.
OK.
So let's write down the Triton kernel.
And in some sense, the form is going to be very similar.
Just like in the GeLU.
Right, once you do the scaffolding,
the core computation looks very much like the naive version.
So what we're going to do is we're going
to say each row is a block.
OK.
And why do I make each row a block?
Well, because now, remember, each row,
I have to normalize and sum.
So it's not element-wise.
So softmax is not element-wise.
But it is row-wise.
So the blocks don't interact.
And the blocks don't have shared memory, so that's fine.
There's no shared memory across blocks.
So then within each row, I'm just going to do some stuff.
OK, so let's see what happens.
So again, I'm going to, in Python,
I'm going to allocate my output tensor.
I have this M by N matrix.
I'm going to define the block size as basically
the number of columns.
Go to the next power of 2 for good luck.
And then the number of blocks is just the number of rows.
OK, and I'm going to call this kernel.
So how many blocks are there?
M.
Right, one for each row.
And each block, I'm going to pass the input pointer,
the output pointer.
And then I'm going to also pass these strides which
tell me how far to move down.
OK, let me actually go and show you that softmax kernel, OK.
OK, so what does this look like here?
So I wake up.
I'm on a particular row, OK.
And this is going to give me all the columns from 0
to the number of block size, which I'm assuming
that's all the columns.
I'm going to read.
So basically, I need to figure out where to read from memory,
and that's going to be the start of my data.
Plus which row.
And the row stride basically gives me
every row is-- basically, this is the number of columns,
essentially.
It's going to tell me where how far to go down.
And then this x pointers is basically the addresses
of all the data I need to load.
I load them up.
And here, I do this thing where if it's masked out, then
I put minus infinity, because that's
going to be the equivalent of a 0 for the softmax operation.
And then this part is essentially the same
as the naive softmax.
I'm just going to compute the max,
subtract it off, exponentiate, sum, and divide.
And then I write it back.
OK.
Yeah.
Yeah, so this is the version where each block can just
span the entire row.
And you can see that Triton makes this very easy, right?
Because this is as if you were just writing normal
PyTorch code.
So if everything fits in a block, you basically—
The thing is, if you can fit it into a block,
you can just write normal PyTorch, almost.
Yeah?
What if my number of columns, the number of rows,
are bigger than blocksize?
Yeah, so we'll get to that.
Now the number of columns, rows, in general,
it's going to be much larger than the blocksize.
So we'll come back to that, yeah.
So if you wanted to do a softmax per column,
So the question is if you want to do softmax by column.
I think that should be fine, because here, we're
tracking these pointers, right.
So the pointers can be anything.
Basically, I think all you would have to do
is change the stride here to basically access the columns.
Actually, it would be here.
The column offsets, you would just multiply this
by the row stride, I think.
OK, let's move on.
All right, so now, warming up to the matmul.
Suppose that your row doesn't fit into a block.
OK, so what do you do in this case?
So for example, if you have, let's say,
a row that's 4,000 columns, but the blocksize is only 1,024.
So you have to do something here.
So here's the strategy.
We're going to break up the row into tiles.
So in this case, there's going to be four tiles.
And each thread is going to iterate over the tiles
and accumulate a sum.
And then finally at the end, we're
going to do the reduction by summing everything
that each thread produced.
So I'll show you an example of this.
And now I'm switching from softmax
to row sum because it's just easier to think about.
OK, so here, well, this is not very interesting.
The built-in row sum does what you would expect.
So the row sum operation just basically takes a matrix
and then computes the sum of each row, OK.
So just no surprises there.
OK, so conceptually what we're going to do here is as follows.
OK, so each block is still in charge of one row.
So that part hasn't changed.
So suppose block one, row one.
I wake up, and what do I do?
I'm going to remember, now, there's tiles.
And suppose tile 0 is columns 0 through 3,
tile 1 is columns 4 through 7.
And then tile 2 is columns 8 through 11.
OK, so what I'm going to do here is
that I'm going to iterate now.
So first, I basically process this, all the threads.
Basically, each thread keeps a kind of accumulator
and processes the first tile.
And it's going to move on to the next tile,
and it's going to add the current element to the accumulator.
So here, I'm putting 3, 1, 4, 1.
And then the second loop iteration,
I'm going to add 5 to this.
I get 8.
I add 9 to this, I get 10.
2 to 4, and 6 to 1, right.
So each of these four threads is going
to be accumulating its own thing.
And then at the end, I do another for tile 2.
I add 5 and 3 to the respective accumulators.
So at the end of the day, I have this, a vector of accumulators.
And then that is actually--that, I can just sum up.
OK, so let's see what the code looks like here.
So I'm just going to call the row sum kernel.
And let's see.
OK, so here's what it looks like.
So wake up.
I am on a particular row.
And this is what one row looks like.
There's one tile, a second tile, a third tile, and so on.
So n is the number of elements of that row.
And block size is the size of this tile.
OK.
So remember, block size is the number of threads.
I'm processing more data than the larger than the block size.
I just have to do it iteratively now.
So I'm going to loop over all of the tiles.
So start is going to go from 0 to block size
to 2 times block size, and so on and so forth.
So each time I'm jumping across, I am doing calls.
Basically get the offsets at the particular tile.
And then I'm going to load the data from HBM,
and I'm going to add it to the accumulation.
So this accumulation is going to be either in registers or shared
memory.
OK.
And then finally after I loop over all the tiles,
I process the whole row, I get basically--
for every thread I have accumulator of what
that thread has picked up.
And I can just do a sum to get a scalar, and I write it out.
OK, so this is a little bit more complicated than before,
because now we have a for loop within a thread.
And this is necessary when your data doesn't fit within a block.
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
Just in case we don't have enough registers.
We have to put it in--
Yeah, so the question is I think if you can control
where the accumulator resides.
At least in this Triton program, you don't explicitly say.
And this is up to the Triton compiler
to figure out where to put it.
But in general, if the block size is large enough,
it has to go in shared memory.
OK.
All right, does this make sense?
Just to, I think, make sure people are on the same page.
Remember when GeLU, we also split a row
into a bunch of pieces.
But those were blocks.
Right, and so each of those pieces
was a block that was processed independently.
These are not blocks.
These are tiles.
The block corresponds to this whole row.
And the block has to basically process all the tiles.
And so this is where it starts to not look like PyTorch,
because you're not able to process all
your data in one nice kind of--
not everything fits into shared memory.
Yeah?
also stored in shared memory?
Yeah.
Let's say the accumulator is stored in shared memory.
OK.
All right, so let's now maybe go on
to our finale, which is matmul.
OK, so matmul, of course, is the bread and butter
of deep learning.
It's been optimized to death.
And it's, in some sense, very fundamental operation.
So you take two matrices, you multiply them.
I'm going to add a little bit of a twist here.
I'm going to do a matmul followed by a ReLU,
just because, just for kicks.
OK.
Well, this happens, right.
Because if you have one linear layer, it's a matmul.
And then you apply a ReLU activation.
So this is not completely out of nowhere.
But I'll show you later why I did this.
OK, so how do you build a matmul kernel?
All right, so here's a naive approach.
OK, so here's my, let's say, a matrix.
I'm multiplying A times B. And I'm
trying to write out the matrix C. And A is M by K, B is K by N.
So C is M by N. OK, so what I'm going to do
is I'm going to fix one of these elements.
Let's say M equals 1, N equals 2.
OK, so I'm processing-- actually, let's do M equals 1,
N equals 1.
So I'm doing C5.
And then, basically for every k, so I'm going to, yeah,
I'm going to iterate over the k, the rows of A
and the columns of B. I'm going to read from HBM.
I'm going to multiply them, accumulate that.
And at the end, I'm going to write out
to this and this element.
So that is a valid matmul kernel.
OK.
So what's wrong with it?
It's correct.
But if you look at how many reads and writes it's doing,
this is not good.
Right, so basically for every M and N and K,
I have to read from HBM.
So it's on the order of M times K times N reads.
Number of writes.
I mean, it doesn't matter, but this is the bottleneck, right.
And if you remember from the second lecture,
if you look at the number of operations
you're doing divided by the number of bytes that
were transferred, that's the arithmetic intensity
which you want to be high.
So the number of operations is M times K times N order.
And then the number of reads is also the same.
So arithmetic intensity is a constant, which is not good.
OK, so if you look carefully, you
notice that there is a lot of redundant reads.
So imagine computing C4.
You needed to read A4, A5, and A6.
And if you compute C5, you're going
to have to read those over again as well.
So if you can just read those once,
then you really save on reads, and that's great.
So let's try to use shared memory to do that.
So here's the idealized approach.
I'm going to load all of A and B into shared memory.
And then I'm going to just compute C. So
if I can do that, then I get--
now I don't have this cubic number of reads,
I only get quadratic number of reads,
which means I get the arithmetic intensity of order n, which
in the second lecture, I said was a kind of ideal thing
you could hope for.
OK, so if you can do that, that's
great, because you basically-- there's no redundant reads.
You read everything once into shared memory.
You do the computation and you write it back.
OK, but what's the problem with this idealized approach?
The problem is that A and B are usually
too large to fit into shared memory.
Right.
So then, what do you have to do now?
OK, so the idea here is this very classic idea of tiling.
And the idea basically is to, well, fit as much
as you can to shared memory as you can, essentially.
So in some sense, it's going to look
like the naive-- it's going to globally look like the naive
approach, but locally it looks like the idealized approach
is the way to think about it.
So here's the picture.
I think Tatsu showed this as well.
So what we're going to do is we're
going to take this matrix C, and instead-- remember,
the naive approach just said for every element,
I'm going to compute it.
But now I'm going to say for every tile, I'm going to do it.
So I break it up into tiles.
And each of these tiles is going to be a thread block.
And I'm going to have a bunch of threads that is
responsible for computing this.
Now a different tile is going to be
computed completely separately by another thread block.
OK, so I'm going to--imagine I'm in Triton.
I wake up.
I'm looking at this thread block.
So what do I have to do?
Well, in some sense, it's the same
as the naive approach where, for every row tile of A,
I'm going to go scan across the rows.
And for every column tile of B, I'm
going to load the corresponding tile A and the corresponding--
so say I'm here-- and the corresponding tile
from B into shared memory.
I'm going to multiply these two together.
And that's going to be like the idealized approach.
And I'm going to accumulate that in the partial sum.
And this is all sitting in shared memory.
And then after I finish all the sweep of the row and the column
here, then I can finally write this output tile to HBM.
OK, so that's conceptually what's happening.
And then the arithmetic intensity here
now goes up to order tile size.
So you can generally not reach order n,
because that would require you to fit everything
into shared memory.
But if your tiles are big, then that's still not too bad.
OK, so just as a bonus.
While you're doing all writing a kernel for this
anyway, sometimes if you want to apply an element-wise activation
function, it's very easy to just put it on at the end.
And this is kernel fusion.
OK, so very quickly, the implementation here.
So-- oops.
OK, so just a reminder about strides since this is going to show up.
So a tensor is a multidimensional array.
But in memory, it's linearized.
And strides of a tensor tells you basically
how to map from a multidimensional index
such as a row, a column, into an actual index.
And basically what you do is multiply the row
by the stride, plus the column
by the stride of the column.
OK, so in this case, every time you advance to the next row,
you go four positions in your memory.
And every time you advance a column, you go one.
And if it were to transpose, it would be flipped.
OK, so what does this kernel look like here?
OK, so the launch is not interesting.
So you wake up and you are on tile M and N.
So it's like OK, I'm responsible for computing the C matrix,
but for the M comma N tile there's
a bunch of index manipulation which you can--
I'll just gloss through, but it's straightforward
but a little bit.
You just have to track the indices.
So this basically tells you which rows of A, the matrix A,
I'm looking at.
Which rows of-- oh sorry, which columns of B I'm looking at.
And then this is just the numbers 1 through K.
Then I'm going to get the pointers into A and B
at my tile location.
And then I'm going to set up this accumulator matrix.
This is going to be in shared memory.
It's M by N. And then this is going
to look like the row reduction, right.
You have this sum over all the tiles.
But instead of just going across the tiles,
I'm now going across the row tiles
and also simultaneously down the column
tiles of B. I load A, the small matrix, I load B, the small B
tile.
And then I perform this dot.
So remember, whenever things are in shared memory,
things look like PyTorch and I can just say, matmul it,
and it will do the thing.
And then I advance to the next row tile of A
and the next column tile of B.
The bonus is that if I wanted to apply
element-wise non-linearity, I might as well do that here.
Before I write it out to HBM, I can do any operation on it.
And then finally, I just write it out.
OK, so there are some indices that you have to pay attention to.
But hopefully, the form of the algorithm is clear.
OK.
Any questions about that?
All right.
Maybe I'll just summarize, and you can ask me later.
So today, we talked about there's
a programming model, which is you're
talking about either PyTorch or Triton or PTX.
This is what the kind of programmer can control.
Right, and even PTX.
You can write PTX and you can control every-- specialize
however you want.
But this is not the full picture,
because the reality is that your code has to run on hardware,
and there's only a finite number of SMs,
a finite number of banks, and sizing of memory and registers.
All are finite.
So you come in with your big matrix and transformer,
and want to-- it has to fit in with the constraints
of the hardware.
So that's why benchmarking and profiling
are really important to understand
how the messiness of the hardware translates to performance.
We talked about Triton, which is,
I think, a pretty nice, neat language to think
about thread blocks.
Hopefully by now you can appreciate
that things are easier to think about thread blocks
than individual threads, because you don't have
to think about explicitly synchronizing threads or doing
shared memory.
And the way to think about it is that you figure out-- you
have your computation.
You break it down into the thread
blocks where you just need to read from shared memory.
Do some stuff, and write it back into HBM.
And then we saw some examples of increasing difficulty.
Element wise is the easiest.
And then reduction over a row.
Reduction where it doesn't fit into a row.
And we introduced the baby tiling.
And then matmul is the canonical example
where you actually do tiling.
OK, so that's all I'm going to say about how
to program a single GPU.
Next time, we're going to go to more GPU and talk
about multi-GPU programming.
Yeah, question.
So if I want to write down kernels,
what are the alternatives?
Do I have to try them and--
for each of my choices that I have,
how close can I get to the optimal level?
So the question is, what are alternatives to Triton?
So there's a trade-off between--
Every language has an inductive bias, right.
That makes certain things easier and certain things harder.
So most of what we do--
Triton was built by people who train transformers.
So anything involving transformers,
I think it's going to be relatively easy there.
Of course, in the extreme, you can always
go to PTX and write that.
But I wouldn't advise that as a first step.
There are a bunch of other libraries.
There's ThunderKittens.
There's CUTE, various DSLs that
allow you to give you-- they're not necessarily comparable
either up or down the stack.
They just give you different characteristics.
Yeah?
Do you have a high dimensional tensor magnification
or high dimensional tensor processing?
What is the best approach?
What I'm thinking is can I load unload the whole tensor, both
of the tensors on bunch of threads or thread blocks
on my GPU at the same time and compute them?
Or would it be better to take each element,
just what we did here, right.
A particular component of my sensor,
then process it and then write it back in the end.
Yeah, so briefly, the question-- and we should probably wrap up--
is, is it better to read all at once
or maybe process individual elements at a time?
I think it's hard to answer this in the abstract.
It depends on the nature of the computation.
Maybe we can talk offline about that.
OK, all right.
See you next time.